Guide to the Time Inc. Corporate Public Affairs Department Records 1945-2000 (bulk 1959-1996) MS 3009-RG 19
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Corporate Public Affairs Department Records
1945-2000 (bulk 1959-1996)
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 19
109 Linear feet (110 boxes, 35 reels of microfilm)
Corporate Public Affairs Department Records contain the office files from Vice President Donald Wilson, the chronological correspondence from Associate Director Louis Slovinsky, office files from the Radio/TV Publicity Office, project files from Community Relations, office files from the Chief Speechwriter, office files from the Special Events Manager, files on exhibitions and contests to promote Time Inc. internationally, and general files produced or collected by the department overall including annual reports, press releases, dinner books, weekly news clippings, and administrative files.
Arrangement Note
Organized into eight series:
Series I. Vice President Donald Wilson Files
Series II. Associate Director Louis Slovinsky Chron Files
Series III. Radio/TV Publicity Office Files
Series IV. Corporate Community Relations Office Files
Series V. Chief Speechwriter Peter Quinn Files
Series VI. Special Events Manager Ann Bellows Files
Series VII. Time Life International/Corporate International Files on Exhibitions and Contests
Series VIII. General Files
Historical Note
In the 1949 Time Inc. Department Heads List in the Time Inc. Reference Files, the earliest in the archives, Corporate Publicity and the FYI company newsletter editor are listed as part of Corporate Special Projects. The listing remains the same through 1960 although Corporate Publicity increases in staff. In 1963 Publicity is listed as overseen by VP and Secretary Bernard Barnes. James Pitt is listed as director with several assistants, including Lucille Nunes. By 1966 Louis Slovinsky is also one of these assistants. In 1968, Publicity has moved under the President's office as part of corporate public affairs which is headed by Bernard Yudain with the title Assistant to the President for Public Affairs. Pitt and Slovinsky continue in their same roles.
In 1970 Time Inc. names Donald Wilson as the vice president of Corporate Public Affairs creating a new department overseeing a public affairs director, corporate contributions director, and the FYI editor. Robert Sweeney served as the first public affairs director in this new department with James Alberse as his deputy. By 1972 Slovinsky is listed as the public relations manager. In 1974 Stan Kapner replaces Alberse as deputy which is now called associate director. Marilyn Sahner joins as the radio/TV publicity manager, and Nunes joins as Midwest public affairs manager. By 1978 Corporate Public Affairs includes the vice president of government affairs, public affairs director, Corporate Creative Services, and Corporate Contributions. Kapner has replaced Sweeney as public affairs director with Slovinsky as associate director as well as public relations manager. By 1980 Slovinsky is the public affairs director. In the 1980s, Corporate Public Affairs adds directors of public policy development, community policy development, tax policy development in 1983. A memo from CEO J. Richard Munro in September 1986 announces that Wilson, therefore Corporate Public Affairs, will begin reporting to Executive Vice President of Strategy and Planning Gerald "Jerry" Levin. By 1987 Corporate Public Affairs includes the positions of director of corporate community relations and chief speechwriter.
Corporate Community Relations created and implemented social programs that provide a service to the community, the largest being Time To Read; oversaw company sponsored volunteer programs; registered minority and women owned or operated businesses with the Time Inc. Minority Business Development Program and published a directory; and represented Time Inc. at meetings of organizations such as the Business Council for Effective Literacy, Magazine Publishers Association, and Corporate Volunteers Coordinators Council.
Corporate Contributions was formalized as an office in 1978 although Time Inc. had been granting funds since 1934. It awarded grants to non-project organizations in the areas of education, art and culture, civic and welfare needs, and the environment.
Corporate Creative Services produced films, presentations, and other materials for meetings such as the Board of Directors, personnel orientation, ATC Franchise Presentation, and Time Ad Sales. It also marketing the use of the Picgture Collection; consulted on the renovation of presentation spaces; and oversaw exhibits in the Time Inc. buildings or traveling exhibits sponsored by Time Inc.
Corporate Cultural Affairs oversaw exhibits sponsored by Time Inc., art commissions made by Time Inc., and cultural exchanges involving exhibitions; and reviewed requests for exhibit and art project corporate sponsorship. This office may have replaced Creative Services.
Government Relations monitored federal goverment activities and reported to Time Inc. executives on topics that affected the company such as taxes, cable providers, postal rates, business regularions, employee benefits, and advertising.
Citation:
Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include privileged attorney correspondence; personnel performance evaluations; contracts and agreements; and records with personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in boxes R24-R26. Materials created within the past 35 years also may be subject to restriction on a case-by-case basis. Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Scope and Contents Note
Corporate Public Affairs Department Records contain the office files from Vice President Donald Wilson, the chronological correspondence from Associate Director Louis Slovinsky, office files from the Radio/TV Publicity Office, project files from Community Relations, office files from the Chief Speechwriter, office files from the Special Events Manager, files on exhibitions and contests to promote Time Inc. internationally, and general files produced or collected by the department overall including annual reports, press releases, dinner books, weekly news clippings, and administrative files.
Provenance
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Annual reports.; Corporation records; Corporations -- History; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporations -- Public relations; Exhibition records.; Organization files; Press clippings.; Press releases; Public relations; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Traveling exhibitions.; Quinn, Peter (Peter A.); Sahner, Marilyn; Slovinsky, Louis J.; Wilson, Donald M.; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History
- Series I. Vice President Donald Wilson Files, 1960-1994; 1968-1989; 218328; 62.5 Linear feet (63 boxes)
  Biographical Note
  Donald M. Wilson served as the vice president of the Time Inc. Corporate Public Affairs Department for 19 years. After graduating from Yale University in 1949, Life hired Wilson as a reporter. He worked as a Life foreign correspondent and the Washington bureau chief prior to leaving the magazine to join John F. Kennedy's presidential campaign as the assistant press secretary. After the election, Kennedy appointed Wilson as deputy director of United States Information Agency (USIA) under director Edward R. Murrow, and he served in this post until 1965. In 1962 Wilson represented USIA on the the Executive Committee of the National Security Council (ExCOMM), a group advising Kennedy during the Cuban Missile Crisis. In 1965, Wilson returned to Time Inc. as general manager of Time-Life International. He was named corporate vice president for public affairs in 1970 and senior vice president in 1985, serving in this role until his retirement from Time Inc. in 1989. After his retirement, Wilson continued as a consultant with Time Inc.
  As vice president of Corporate Public Affairs, Wilson was responsible for the corporate message, examining how actions by Time Inc. reflected on its image and responding when necessary, monitoring other media reporting on Time Inc., and overseeing major corporate image undertakings by Time Inc.
  Citation: Donald M. Wilson obituary. The Times, Trenton, December 11, 2011. Accessed February 5, 2018. http://obits.nj.com/obituaries/trenton/obituary.aspx?pid=155005033
  Scope and Contents Note
  Vice President Donald Wilson Files contain Wilson's correspondence and other office files and work product. Records include updates on the activities and accomplishments of offices within Corporation Public Affairs such as Corporate Community Relations (Director Toni Fay), Corporate Contributions (Director and later Vice President Jeanne Kerr), Corporate Creative Services (Director Enfield "Flicky" Ford), Corporate Cultural Affairs (Director Zachary Morfogen), Radio/TV Publicity (Director Marilyn Sahner), and Government Relations (Vice Presidents Barry Zorthian, John Steele, Brian Conboy).
  Records also include correspondence and memoranda, press releases and internal discussion and revisions by executives or other Corporate Public Affairs staff; Time Inc. official statements; annual shareholder meeting official questions and answers for events such as annual shareholder meetings or subsidiary acquisitions and mergers; speeches from various Time Inc. executives; departmental newsletters; subsidiary press kits and newsletters; art exhibit plans and brochures; and new clippings.
  The general Miscellaneous Memoranda files contain outside requests for participation in events, programs and associations; offers of consulting services; surveys from outside researchers; correspondence and other materials from associations of which Time Inc. was a member or of which a Time Inc. officer was a board member; invitations from universities to interview graduates; fundraising requests; a few reader complaints regarding non-editorial issues; and vendor introductions. Wilson advises Time Inc. executives on these matters in the specific Miscellaneous Memoranda files. Miscellaneous Requests contain similar materials, but with more corporate sponsorship requests.
  Major events covered by his files include reconfiguring the corporate identity including creating a definite Time Inc. logo; environmental complaints against Eastex Inc. during the proposed creation of Big Thicket National Park; the Howard Hughes hoax autobiography manuscript; review of South African employment practices after development of the Sullivan principles; subsidiary sales, acquisitions, and mergers; court proceedings including Ariel Sharon's libel suit against Time Inc.; reports that Nikita Khrushchev disavowed his recollections published in Life ahead of the publication of his memoirs; and planning materials for an unrealized exhibit in the new EPCOT Center; and Time Inc.'s participation in political action committees.
  Items of interest include a 1986 memo from Director of Corporate Public Affairs Louis Slovinsky regarding a search for a Time Inc. promotional tag line; praise from New York City Commissioner for the United Nations and Consular Corps Gillian Sorensen on a presentation by Time Inc. and related discussion session between ambassadors and Time Inc. executives; a 1979 memo from Time Inc. Archivist Lillian Owens summarizing her review of the archives related to claims that Henry Luce received money from the Iranian Shah; and an illustrated flyer advocating for a better contract for Newspaper Guild members.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized alphabetically based on the original order with some rearranging to fit files into the alphabetical scheme. A folder of forms transferring material to the archives is at the front.
  - Archives Transfer Forms, 1989; 218626 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 1)
  - Acme, 1985; 218627 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 2)
    Regarding a joint venture with AT&T, Bank of America, and Chemical Bank.
  - Advertising Expenditure Survey, 1982; 218628 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 3)
  - Affirmative Action Program, 1984-1985; 218631 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 4)
  - Age Discrimination, 1985; 218632 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 5)
  - Alexander Project ("The Search for Alexander" Exhibit), 1981-1984; 218633 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 6-10)
  - American Corporate Aid to Lebanon: General, 1982; 223851 (Offsite-box 1857, Folder 1-3)
  - American Corporate Aid to Lebanon: Aid Situation Report, 1982; 223852 (Offsite-box 1857, Folder 4)
  - American Corporate Aid to Lebanon: Form 1023 Section 501(c) 3, 1982; 223853 (Offsite-box 1857, Folder 5)
  - American Corporate Aid to Lebanon: News Releases and Statement of Purpose, 1982; 223854 (Offsite-box 1857, Folder 6)
  - American Corporate Aid to Lebanon: Solicitation Letter and Responses, 1982; 223855 (Offsite-box 1857, Folder 7)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): General, 1978-1988; 218634 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 11-16)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC) and TBS, 1987; 218635 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 17)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Community Programming/Public Affairs Conference, 1985; 218636 (Offsite-box 1634, Folder 18)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Conference, 1984-1986; 218638 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 1-2)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Executive Office Move, 1988; 218639 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 3)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Merger (Acquisition by Time Inc.), 1977-1978; 218640 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 4)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Merger (Acquisition by Time Inc.) [RESTRICTED], 219883 (Offsite-box R24)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Public Affairs and Community Programming Conference, 1986; 218641 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 5)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Stock Sale, 1986; 218642 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 6)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Storer Communications, 1987; 218643 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 7)
  - American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC): Thayer Bigelow Announcement (ATC President Appointment), 1987-1988; 218645 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 8)
  - Analyst Meetings (Financial), 1984-1988; 218647 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 9-13)
  - Analyst Reports (of Time Inc. Stock), 1986-1987; 218648 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 14-15)
  - Annual Meetings, 1982; 218649 (Offsite-box 1635, Folder 16-18)
    Records include briefing books, questions and answers, special procedures manuals, and remarks by Time Inc. executives.
  - Annual Meetings, 1983-1988; 218651 (Offsite-box 1636, Folder 1-11)
  - Annual Reports, 1982-1983; 218652 (Offsite-box 1636, Folder 12-13)
    Annual Report folders include preparation materials and the published report.
  - Annual Reports, 1984-1987; 218653 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 1-5)
  - Antitrust Conference, 1979; 218654 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 6)
  - Archives (Time Inc.), 1960-1988; 218655 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 7-8)
  - Articles: Bernstein, Lester: New York Times, 1988; 218656 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 9)
  - Articles: Business Week Interview, 1984; 218658 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 10)
  - Articles: Byron, Chris: Book, 1984-1986; 218657 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 11-13)
  - Articles: Interviews of Time Inc. Executives in Other Media, 1978-1982; 218660 (Offsite-box 1637, Folder 14-15)
  - Articles: Interviews with Time Inc. Executives in Other Media, 1983-1989; 218704 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 1-5)
  - Articles: Dow Joneser, 1987-1988; 218705 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 6)
  - Articles: Ayco Corporation, 1978; 218706 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 7)
  - Bear, Charles: Retirement, 1984; 218707 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 8)
  - Benton, Nick: Retirement, 1983; 218708 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 9)
  - Benton, Nick: Retirement [RESTRICTED], 219884 (Offsite-box R24)
  - Bernstein, Lester: New York Times Magazine, 1988; 218709 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 10)
  - Biographies of Executives, 1982-1986; 218710 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 11-13)
  - Board of Directors, 1979-1988; 218711 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 14-15)
  - Board Dinner, 1988; 218712 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 16)
  - Bonuses: Special, 1987; 218713 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 17)
  - Book Club and Book-of-the-Month Club Merger, 1977; 218714 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 18)
  - Book Club and Book-of-the-Month Club Merger [RESTRICTED], 219885 (Offsite-box R24)
  - Book-of-the-Month Club, 1979-1987; 218715 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 19-20)
  - Book-of-the-Month Club Merger, 1977; 218716 (Offsite-box 1638, Folder 21)
  - Book-of-the-Month Club Merger [RESTRICTED], 219886 (Offsite-box R24)
  - Books and Arts Associates Meetings in Brazil, 1978; 218717 (Offsite-box 1639, Folder 1)
  - Budget: General, 1984-1988; 218718 (Offsite-box 1639, Folder 2-5)
  - Budget: Corporate Community Relations, 1987; 218719 (Offsite-box 1639, Folder 6)
  - Budget: Five Year Plan: Government Affairs, Corporate Public Affairs, Corporate Contributions, 1980; 218720 (Offsite-box 1639, Folder 7)
  - Budget: Public Affairs, 1970-1986; 218721 (Offsite-box 1639, Folder 8-16)
  - Budget: Public Affairs, 1987-1988; 218722 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 1-6)
  - Burson-Marsteller Proposal, 1986; 218723 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 7)
  - Business and the Press, 1975; 218725 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 8)
  - Byron, Chris, 1984-1986; 218726 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 9)
  - Cafeteria Plans Out Card [see Reference Files], 1983; 218727 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 10)
  - Case Meeting on Higher Education, 1988; 218728 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 11)
  - Center for Strategic and International Studies, 1988; 218729 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 12)
  - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) and the Press, 1986; 218730 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 13)
  - Chamber of Commerce of the United States Meeting, 1981; 218731 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 14)
  - Chicago Relocation of Time Inc. Offices, 1986; 218732 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 15-17)
  - Chicago Retirees' Alumni Program, 1987; 218733 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 18)
  - Cigarette Advertising Statement, 1985; 218734 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 19)
  - Citizens Committee for Restoring Public Trust in Government, 1977; 218735 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 20)
  - City at 42nd Street (A Celebration of Cities), 1979; 218736 (Offsite-box 1640, Folder 21)
  - Clips: 1986-1988 April, 218737 (Offsite-box 1641)
  - Clips: 1988 May-December, 218816 (Offsite-box 1642)
  - Clips: 1988 October-1989 January, 1988-1989; 218820 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 1-3)
  - Clips: Cost Cutting Layoffs, 1985-1986; 218821 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 4)
  - Clips: Important Stories in 1985, 218822 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 5)
  - Clips: Staff Reductions in Other Companies, 1986-1987; 218823 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 6)
  - Clips: Time Inc., 1984-1987; 218827 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 7)
  - Columbia University: Chair at Journalistm School, 1985; 218829 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 8)
  - Columbia University: Minority Student Lunches, 1979-1980; 218830 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Technology Report, 1985; 218831 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 10)
  - Community Activities of Time Inc. Executives, 1974; 218833 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 11)
  - Conboy, Brian, 1987-1988; 218835 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 12-14)
  - Conference on Electoral Reform, 1981; 218836 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 15)
  - Conferences: Dinner and Luncheon Invitations, 1986-1987; 218838 (Offsite-box 1643, Folder 16-20)
  - Conferences: Dinner and Luncheon Invitations, 1987-1988; 218841 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 1-4)
  - Congressional Letter to Districts, 1975-1976; 218843 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 5)
  - Contributions: Beirut University College, 1985-1986; 218845 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 6)
  - Conventions, 1976; 218846 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 7)
  - Corporate: General, 1983-1987; 218848 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 8-11)
    Includes information on Time Inc. and subsidiary stock, revenues and expenditures, invenstory relations, organizational effectiveness, and the Time Inc. Foundation.
  - Corporate: Ad Campaign, 1981-1986; 218851 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 12)
  - Corporate: Aircraft, 1977-1986; 218853 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 13)
  - Corporate: American Revival (Editorial Coverage in Each Magazine), 1980-1981; 218854 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 14)
  - Corporate: Announcement of New Officers, 1985; 218855 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 15)
  - Corporate: Announcement: Jerry Levin on Books and Selling Areas-Marketing, Inc. (SAMI), 1985; 218859 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 16)
  - Corporate: Art Collection, 1978; 218860 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 17)
  - Corporate: Benefits Changes, 1987; 218861 (Offsite-box 1644, Folder 18-19)
  - Corporate: Booklet: "It's About Time", 1979; 218862 (Offsite-box 1645, Folder 1)
  - Corporate: Booklet: "The New Time Inc.", 1983-1984; 218863 (Offsite-box 1645, Folder 2)
  - Corporate: Brack and Fuchs Appointments, 1987; 218866 (Offsite-box 1645, Folder 3)
  - Corporate: Brack and Sutton Appointments, 1986; 218867 (Offsite-box 1645, Folder 4)
  - Corporate: Bureaucracy Committee, 1985; 218868 (Offsite-box 1645, Folder 5)
  - Corporate Community Relations: General, 1985-1987; 218870 (Offsite-box 1645, Folder 6-15)
    Corporate Community Relations folders contain primarily materials on the programs Time to Read and and Minority Business Development, including copies of the Time Inc. Directory of Minority Business Enterprises and Time Inc. Purchasing Directory for Minority and Women-Owned Business Firms.
  - Corporate Community Relations: General, 1988; 218954 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 1-2)
  - Corporate Community Relations: Time to Read, 1986-1988; 218956 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 3-8)
    Includes memoranda to and from the Corporate Contributions Committee.
  - Corporate: Computer (Information Systems Executive Briefing), 1982; 218958 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 9)
  - Corporate Contributions: Board Memorandum, 1983; 218960 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 10)
  - Corporate Contributions: Budgets, 1983-1984; 218961 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 11-12)
  - Corporate Contributions: Correspondence with Robert Steed (Human Relations), 1981; 218962 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 13)
  - Corporate Contributions: National Urban Coalition, 1983; 218967 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 14)
  - Corporate Contributions: Yale Law School, 1983; 218968 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 15)
  - Corporate: Correspondence: Wage and Price Stability (Inflation), 1978-1979; 218964 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 16)
    Includes correspondence from the White House.
  - Corporate: Cost Management, 1985-1986; 218969 (Offsite-box 1646, Folder 17-18)
  - Corporate Creative Services, 1978-1984; 218973 (Offsite-box 1647, Folder 1-2)
  - Corporate: Crimes Against Business [RESTRICTED], 1978; 219887 (Offsite-box R24)
  - Corporate Cultural Affairs: General, 1986; 218974 (Offsite-box 1647, Folder 3-6)
  - Corporate Cultural Affairs: Time Inc. Honors Program, 1984-1985; 218975 (Offsite-box 1647, Folder 7)
  - Corporate: Dinner for Ronald Reagan, 1981; 218978 (Offsite-box 1647, Folder 8)
  - Corporate: Executive Calendar, 1985; 218979 (Offsite-box 1647, Folder 9)